<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French Revolution</title>
            <author>Thomas Carlyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Exercise file for Textual Editing in the Digital Age, April 2019.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Snippet from the first chapter, copied from Project Gutenberg.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 1.1.I. Louis the Well-Beloved.</head>

         <p>President Henault, remarking on royal Surnames of Honour how difficult it often is to
            ascertain not only why, but even when, they were conferred, takes occasion in his sleek
            official way, to make a philosophical reflection. 'The Surname of Bien-aime
            (Well-beloved),' says he, 'which Louis XV. bears, will not leave posterity in the same
            doubt. This Prince, in the year 1744, while hastening from one end of his kingdom to the
            other, and suspending his conquests in Flanders that he might fly to the assistance of
            Alsace, was arrested at Metz by a malady which threatened to cut short his days. At the
            news of this, Paris, all in terror, seemed a city taken by storm: the churches resounded
            with supplications and groans; the prayers of priests and people were every moment
            interrupted by their sobs: and it was from an interest so dear and tender that this
            Surname of Bien-aime fashioned itself, a title higher still than all the rest which this
            great Prince has earned.' (Abrege Chronologique de l'Histoire de France (Paris, 1775),
            p. 701.)</p>

         <p>So stands it written; in lasting memorial of that year 1744. Thirty other years have
            come and gone; and 'this great Prince' again lies sick; but in how altered circumstances
            now! Churches resound not with excessive groanings; Paris is stoically calm: sobs
            interrupt no prayers, for indeed none are offered; except Priests' Litanies, read or
            chanted at fixed money-rate per hour, which are not liable to interruption. The shepherd
            of the people has been carried home from Little Trianon, heavy of heart, and been put to
            bed in his own Chateau of Versailles: the flock knows it, and heeds it not. At most, in
            the immeasurable tide of French Speech (which ceases not day after day, and only ebbs
            towards the short hours of night), may this of the royal sickness emerge from time to
            time as an article of news. Bets are doubtless depending; nay, some people 'express
            themselves loudly in the streets.' (Memoires de M. le Baron Besenval (Paris, 1805), ii.
            59-90.) But for the rest, on green field and steepled city, the May sun shines out, the
            May evening fades; and men ply their useful or useless business as if no Louis lay in
            danger.</p>

         <p>Dame Dubarry, indeed, might pray, if she had a talent for it; Duke d'Aiguillon too,
            Maupeou and the Parlement Maupeou: these, as they sit in their high places, with France
            harnessed under their feet, know well on what basis they continue there. Look to it,
            D'Aiguillon; sharply as thou didst, from the Mill of St. Cast, on Quiberon and the
            invading English; thou, 'covered if not with glory yet with meal!' Fortune was ever
            accounted inconstant: and each dog has but his day.</p>

         <p>Forlorn enough languished Duke d'Aiguillon, some years ago; covered, as we said, with
            meal; nay with worse. For La Chalotais, the Breton Parlementeer, accused him not only of
            poltroonery and tyranny, but even of concussion (official plunder of money); which
            accusations it was easier to get 'quashed' by backstairs Influences than to get
            answered: neither could the thoughts, or even the tongues, of men be tied. Thus, under
            disastrous eclipse, had this grand-nephew of the great Richelieu to glide about;
            unworshipped by the world; resolute Choiseul, the abrupt proud man, disdaining him, or
            even forgetting him. Little prospect but to glide into Gascony, to rebuild Chateaus
            there, (Arthur Young, Travels during the years 1787-88-89 (Bury St. Edmunds, 1792), i.
            44.) and die inglorious killing game! However, in the year 1770, a certain young
            soldier, Dumouriez by name, returning from Corsica, could see 'with sorrow, at
            Compiegne, the old King of France, on foot, with doffed hat, in sight of his army, at
            the side of a magnificent phaeton, doing homage the—Dubarry.' (La Vie et les Memoires du
            General Dumouriez (Paris, 1822), i. 141.)</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
